CONTACT DETAILS

University of Chicago

Department of Statistics & Data Science Institute

5735 S Ellis Ave

Chicago, IL 10027, 60637

Telephone: +1 (650) 656-0855 E-mail: ignat@uchicago.edu

Website: https://nignatiadis.github.io/ Google Scholar: user=KH3jpkoAAAAJ

Last update: July 5, 2023

RESEARCH INTERESTS I am interested in the development of interpretable statistical methods, accompanied by robust software implementations, for the analysis of datasets generated from modern, high-throughput technologies. From a statistical perspective, this interest encompasses Empirical Bayes analysis, causal inference, multiple testing and statistics in the presence of contextual side-information.

ACADEMIC EMPLOYMENT Department of Statistics and Data Science Institute, University of Chicago, USA

• Assistant Professor

Beginning 07/2023

Department of Statistics, Columbia University

• Postdoctoral Research Scientist

New York, USA 09/2022 - 06/2023

09/2016 - 06/2022

EDUCATION

Stanford University

• Ph.D., Statistics (GPA 4.24)

Thesis advisor: Stefan Wager

Thesis title: Nonparametric perspectives on empirical Bayes.

• M.S., Statistics

Heidelberg University

Heidelberg, Germany

Stanford, California, USA

• M.Sc., Scientific Computing, Grade 1.0

Thesis advisors: Wolfgang Huber and Enno Mammen
• B.Sc., Mathematics, Grade 1.0 with distinction

Thesis advisors: Wolfgang Huber and Rainer Dahlhaus

• B.Sc., Molecular Biotechnology, Grade 1.0

2010 - 2013

2015 - 2016

2011 - 2015

AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

## Jerome H. Friedman Applied Statistics Dissertation Award

2022

For developing methodology that uses side information for increased power in multiple testing problems and for developing approaches to inference in empirical Bayes problems.

#### Ric Weiland Graduate Fellowship in the Humanities & Sciences

2020 - 202

This fellowship is awarded to exceptional rising fourth year doctoral candidates in the humanities, social sciences, mathematics, and statistics upon departmental or programmatic nomination.

Departmental Teaching Assistant Award, Statistics Department, Stanford

2018

iGEM Grand Prize Winner & Best Foundational Advance

2013

The International Genetically Engineered Machine competition with Team Heidelberg at MIT.

Deutschlandstipendium, Heidelberg University, Germany

2011 - 2013

This scholarship is awarded to talented and high-achieving students at public and state recognised institutions of higher education in Germany and is supported by the German Federal Government.

Bronze medal at the International Biology Olympiad, Changwon, South Korea

2010

Journal Publications

- 1. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Sujayam Saha, Dennis L. Sun, Omkar Muralidharan (2023). Empirical Bayes mean estimation with nonparametric errors via order statistic regression on replicated data. Journal of the American Statistical Association, Theory and Methods, 118(542), 987-999.
- 2. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Stefan Wager (2022). Rejoinder: Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis. Journal of the American Statistical Association, Theory and Methods, 117(539), 1192-1199.
- 3. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Stefan Wager (2022). Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis. Journal of the American Statistical Association, Theory and Methods, 117(539), 1149-1166.

- 4. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Wolfgang Huber (2021). Covariate powered cross-weighted multiple testing. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (JRSS-B), 83(4), 720-751.
- 5. Loukia Karacosta, Benedict Anchang, Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Samuel Kimmey, Jalen Benson, Joseph Shrager, Robert Tibshirani, Sean Bendall, Sylvia K. Plevritis (2019). Mapping lung cancer epithelial-mesenchymal transition states and trajectories with single-cell resolution. Nature communications, 10, 5887.
- 6. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Bernd Klaus, Judith Zaugg, Wolfgang Huber (2016). **Data-driven hypothesis** weighting increases detection power in genome-scale multiple testing. Nature methods, 13(7), 577-580.
- 7. Ralf Beer, Konrad Herbst, Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Ilia Kats, Lorenz Adlung, Hannah Meyer, Dominik Niopek, Tania Christiansen, Fanny Georgi, Nils Kurzawa, Johanna Meichsner, Sophie Rabe, Anja Riedel, Joshua Sachs, Julia Schessner, Florian Schmidt, Philipp Walch, Katharina Niopek, Tim Heinemann, Roland Eils, Barbara Di Ventura (2014). Creating functional engineered variants of the single-module non-ribosomal peptide synthetase IndC by T domain exchange. Molecular BioSystems, 10(7), 1709-1718.

#### Conference Proceedings

- 8. Stephen Pfohl, Yizhe Xu, Agata Foryciarz, Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Julian Genkins, Nigam H. Shah (2022). Net benefit, calibration, threshold selection, and training objectives for algorithmic fairness in healthcare. ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (FAccT'22).
- 9. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Stefan Wager (2019). Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 32 (NeurIPS 2019).

#### BOOK CHAPTERS

10. Yizhe Xu, Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Erik Sverdrup, Scott Fleming, Stefan Wager, Nigam H. Shah (2023). **Treatment Heterogeneity with Survival Outcomes.** Book chapter in: Handbook of Matching and Weighting Adjustments for Causal Inference. Edited by José R. Zubizaretta, Elizabeth A. Stuart, Dylan S. Small, and Paul R. Rosenbaum. Chapman and Hall / CRC Press.

#### Preprints

- 11. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Bodhisattva Sen (2023). Empirical partially Bayes multiple testing and compound  $\chi^2$  decisions. Working paper.
- 12. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Ruodu Wang, Aaditya Ramdas (2022). **E-values as unnormalized weights** in multiple testing. Working paper.
- 13. Dean Eckles, Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Stefan Wager, Han Wu (2022). Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs. Working paper.
- 14. Nikolaos Ignatiadis, Panagiotis Lolas (2021). σ-Ridge: group-regularized ridge regression via empirical Bayes noise level cross-validation. Working paper.

### INVITED DISCUSSIONS

## International Seminar on Selective Inference (ISSI)

December 2020

Discussant of the talk 'Clipper: p-value-free FDR control on high-throughput data from two conditions' by Prof. Jingyi Jessica Li.

#### Peer Review

## Statistics journals

Annals of Statistics (AoS), Bernoulli, Biometrical Journal, Biometrics, Biometrika, Electronic Journal of Statistics (EJS), Journal of the American Statistical Association: Theory & Methods (JASA T&M), Journal of Business & Economic Statistics (JBES), Journal of Causal Inference (JCI), Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics (JCGS), Journal of the Royal Statistical Society—Series B (JRSS-B), Journal of Statistical Software (JSS), Statistical Papers, Statistical Science

#### Other journals

Bioinformatics, Bioinformatics Advances, BMC Medical Research Methodology, Journal of Cell Science, Management Science, Nature Protocols, Operations Research, PeerJ

#### Conferences

AISTATS (2021), NeurIPS (2021, 2022), ICLR (2022)

#### Software

### R packages in Bioconductor:

• IHW: Independent Hypothesis Weighting for multiple testing with side-information.

• IHWpaper: Companion to the IHW package facilitating reproducibility.

#### Julia packages in the official registry:

- Aurora.jl: Empirical Bayes mean estimation with nonparametric errors on replicated data.
- Empirikos.jl: Nonparametric empirical Bayes confidence intervals.
- Regression Discontinuity.jl: Basic functionality for analyzing sharp regression discontinuity designs.
- SigmaRidgeRegression.jl:  $\sigma$ -Ridge for regression with features that can be partitioned into groups.
- SmoothingSplines.jl: Nonparametric regression using smoothing splines.
- Contributions to Distributions.jl, GLM.jl, MultipleTesting.jl and others.

#### INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

## Google AdsMetrics, Mountain View, USA

Summer 2019

Data science intern with Omkar Muralidharan, Sujayam Saha and Dennis L. Sun.

#### RESEARCH APPOINTMENTS

#### Biomedical Informatics, Stanford, California, USA

2021 - 2022

Research assistant in the group of Prof. Nigam Shah funded by the NHLBI R01 grant 'Applying statistical learning tools to personalize cardiovascular treatment'.

## Statistics Department, Stanford, California, USA

2017 - 2021

Research assistant with Prof. Stefan Wager working on empirical Bayes and causal inference problems. **European Molecular Biology Laboratory**, Heidelberg, Germany 2014 - 2016

Research assistant in the group of Dr. Wolfgang Huber.

#### TEACHING

#### **Instructor** at Columbia University

GR8201: Topics in Theoretical Statistics, Empirical Bayes (jointly with Bodhisattva Sen) Spring 2023

**Instructor** at Stanford University

STATS 302: Applied Statistics Ph.D. Qualifying Exam Workshop.

Summer 2020

Winter 2018

## Teaching Assistant (TA) at Stanford University

STATS 315B: Modern Applied Statistics: Data Mining.

Spring 2021
STATS 361: Causal Inference.
Spring 2020
STATS 305B: Applied Statistics II.
Winter 2020
STATS 315A: Modern Applied Statistics: Learning.
STATS 300A: Theory of Statistics I.
STATS 366 (BIOS 221): Modern Statistics for Modern Biology.
STATS 218: Introduction to Stochastic Processes II.
Spring 2021
Spring 2020
Summer 2017 & 2018, Fall 2019
Spring 2018

STATS 290: Computing for Data Science.

STATS 305A: Introduction to Statistical Modeling. Fall 2017 STATS 191: Introduction to Applied Statistics. Winter 2017 STATS 141 (BIOS 141): Biostatistics. Fall 2016

**Trainer** at EMBL (European Molecular Biology Laboratory)

Introductory Course: Statistical Bioinformatics using R and Bioconductor October 2015

## Talks and Presentations

## Empirical partially Bayes multiple testing and compound $\chi^2$ decisions

2023 Berkeley–Columbia Meeting in Engineering and Statistics, Columbia University New York, NY, USA, April 2023

#### Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis

Seminar at Department of Statistics and Data Science, Yale University

New Haven, CT, USA, November 2022

### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Econometrics Colloquium at the Economics Department, Columbia University

New York, NY, USA, November 2022

#### Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis

Statistics Department Seminar at Athens University of Economics and Business (AUEB)

Virtual, October 2022

#### Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation

Seminar (student seminar series) at the Department of Statistics, Columbia University

New York, NY, USA, September 2022

#### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Second Congress of Greek Mathematicians (SCGM)

Virtual, July 2022

## Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis

JASA Theory and Methods Invited Session at the Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM)

Washington, DC, USA, June 2022

## Covariate-powered empirical Bayes estimation

New ideas in empirical Bayes at the 5th International Conference on Econometrics and Statistics (EcoSta 2022)

Virtual, June 2022

#### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Methodological innovations for challenges in health policy and clinical care at the 2022 American Causal Inference Conference

Berkeley, CA, USA, May 2022

# Empirical Bayes Mean Estimation With Nonparametric Errors Via Order Statistic Regression on Replicated Data

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics, UC Davis

Davis, CA, USA, April 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Statistics and Data Science Seminar at the Department of Statistics and Data Science, Carnegie Mellon University

Virtual, February 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics, University of British Columbia

Virtual, February 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics and Data Science, Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania

Virtual, February 2022

## Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Seminar at the Department of Decision Sciences, Bocconi University

Milano, Italy, February 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics, UC Davis

Virtual, January 2022

## Confidence intervals for nonparametric empirical Bayes analysis and an application to regression discontinuity designs

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics, UCLA

Virtual, January 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Seminar at the Data Science Institute, University of Chicago

Chicago, Illinois, USA, January 2022

# Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis and an Application to Regression Discontinuity Designs

Seminar at the Department of Statistics and Actuarial Science, University of Waterloo

Virtual, January 2022

#### Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Inference

Statistics Seminar at the Department of Statistics, Columbia University

Virtual, January 2022

# Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis and an Application to the Regression Discontinuity Design

ACMS Colloquium at Department of Applied and Computational Mathematics and Statistics, University of Notre Dame

Notre Dame, Indiana, USA, December 2021

#### Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis

Advances in Empirical Bayes Methodology at the International Conference on Computational and Methodological Statistics (CMStatistics)

Virtual, December 2021

#### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Fourth Annual Berkeley-Stanford Econometrics Jamboree at UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA, November 2021

#### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Causal Science Conference at Stanford University

Stanford, USA, November 2021

### Noise-Induced Randomization in Regression Discontinuity Designs

Causal Inference When Resources Are Limited at the Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM)

Virtual, August 2021

## Confidence Intervals for Nonparametric Empirical Bayes Analysis

International Seminar on Selective Inference (ISSI)

Virtual, April 2021

### $\sigma$ -Ridge: group regularized ridge regression via empirical Bayes noise level cross-validation

Statistics Seminar at Vrije Universiteit (VU) Amsterdam campus

Virtual, April 2021

# Discussion of 'Clipper: p-value-free FDR control on high-throughput data from two conditions'

Discussant at the International Seminar on Selective Inference (ISSI)

Virtual, December 2020

#### Bias-Aware Confidence Intervals for Empirical Bayes Analysis

Causality in Statistical Data Science at the Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM)

Virtual, August 2020

#### Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation

Blue Seminar at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL)

Heidelberg, Germany, January 2020

#### Covariate-Powered Empirical Bayes Estimation

11th International Conference on Multiple Comparison Procedures at the National Taiwan University (NTU)

Taipei, Taiwan, December 2019

#### Bias-Aware Confidence Intervals for Empirical Bayes Analysis

Atlantic Causal Inference Conference at McGill University

Montreal, Canada, May 2019

## Covariate powered cross-weighted multiple testing

Statistics Industrial Affiliates Conference at Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA, February 2019

#### Covariate-powered cross-weighted multiple testing with FDR Control

Workshop in Post-selection Inference and Multiple Testing at the Institut de Mathématiques de Toulouse Toulouse, France, February 2018

#### MultipleTesting.jl: Simultaneous Statistical Inference in Julia

Lightning talk at JuliaCon

Berkeley, CA, USA, June 2017

#### Data-driven hypothesis weighting increases detection power in genome-scale multiple testing

Genome Biology Seminar at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL)

Heidelberg, Germany, July 2016